In this segment we're gonna look at
another method to achieve chosen plain
这一节我们来学习另一种明文攻击的方法
text security that's actually superior to
CBC. And this method is called randomized
这种方法比CBC（密码分组链接模式）更高级，叫随机计数器模式
counter mode. Unlike CBC. Randomized
counter mode uses a secure PRF. It doesn't
与CBC不同，随机计数模式使用的是更安全的PRF（变量总体回归模型）
need a block cypher. It's enough for
counter mode to just use a PRF because
它不使用分组密码，对于计数器模式而言，PRF对它来说已经足够
we're never going to be inverting this
function F. So we're going to let F be the
因为我们从不求这个函数F的逆。我们设F为一个安全的PRF
secure PRF and it acts on N byte blocks.
Again if we use AES, N will be 128. And
它定义在N字节的分组上，如果我们用AES的话，N会是128
the way the encryption algorithm works in
counter mode is it starts off by choosing
而这种加密算法插入计数器模式是从选择随机数IV开始的
a random IV, that's 128 bytes random IV in
the case of AES, and the essentially we
而在使用AES的情况下它会是一个128字节的随机数IV
start counting. From this random IV, so
you notice the first encryption is of IV
然后我们开始计数，从这个随机数IV开始，你会发现编码会从IV到IV+1，一直到IV+L
then IV+1 up to IV+L. So we generate this
random pad. We XOR the result with the
这样就可以生成一个随机数表，然后让结果和明文信息相异或
message, and that gives us the cipher
text. And, as usual, you notice that the
就获得了密文。而且，通常情况下
IV here is included along with the cipher
text. So that, in fact, the cipher text is
IV已经连同密文包含在内了
a little longer than the original plain
text. And the point, of course, is that,
事实上，这样生成的密文会比原明文长一些
encryption algorithm chooses a new IV for
every message. And so even if I encrypt
而这样的话，加密算法会给每条明文重新选择一个新的IV
the same message twice, I'm gonna get
different resulting cipher texts. One
因此，即使我对同一个明文加密了两次，我也会得到两个不同的密文
thing to notice that this mode is
completely parallelizable, unlike CBC. CBC
需要注意的是，这个模式是完全可并行的，不像CBC，CBC是串行的
was sequential. In other words, you
couldn't encrypt block #5 until you've
换句话说，就是你不可能做到在没有加密#1到#4的情况下对#5进行加密
encrypted blocks ##1 to 4, so
hardware companies who might have multiple
所以，对于那些可能有很多并行AES引擎的硬件公司来说
AES engines working in parallel cannot
actually use those AES engines when using
当在使用CBC的时候，是很难使用AES引擎的，因为CBC本身是串行的
CBC because CBCs inherently sequential. So
even though you might have two or three of
所以，即使你可能有两个三个或四个AES引擎
four AES engines, you could only use one
of them when doing CBC encryption. With
当你在用CBC加密的时候，你也只能使用其中一个引擎
counter mode, everything is completely
paralyzable. If you have three AES engines
用计数器模式时，一切都是完全可并行的。如果你有三个
encryption basically will work three times
as fast. So that's the beauty of counter
AES加密引擎，工作速度会快上三倍，这就是计数器模型的优点
mode. And counter mode also has a
corresponding nonce based counter mode.
计数器模式还有一种基于新鲜值的计数器模式
Where the IV is not truly random, but
rather, is just a nonce which could
在这个区域里IV并不是一个真正的随机数，而是一个新鲜值
be a counter. And the way you would
implement nonce based counter mode, is you
要实现基于新鲜值的计数器模式
would take the 128 bits block that used in
AES. And then you would split it in two.
也就相当于是在AES中获得一个128位分组，然后你可以把它分成两部分
You would use the left 64 bits as the
nonce, so the counter say would count from
使用左边64位作为新鲜值，这样计数器的范围就是
zero to 2 to the 64. And then, that will
be the nonce part of it. And then once you
从0到2的64次方，这就是新鲜值部分
specify the nonce, the lower order, 64
bits, would be doing the counting inside
而一旦你指定了新鲜值，低64位用于
of the counter modes encryption. Okay, so
nonce goes on the left, and the
计数器模型加密过程内计数，然后新鲜值会停留在左边
counter mode encryption counter goes on
the right. And it's perfectly fine if this
而计数器会在右边，倘若新鲜值是不可预知的话
nonce is unpredictable. The only
restriction is that you encrypt at most
那这就已经是非常好的状态了，此时唯一可能限制的情况是
2 to the 64 blocks using one particular
nonce. The danger is that you don't
你最多可以加密2的64次方个分组，使用一个新鲜值
want this counter to reset to zero so
that, then, you will have two blocks. Say,
这个危险情况就是你此时不想将计数器重置为0，如果那样的话你会有两个分组
this guy, this guy, and this guy that are
encrypted using the same one time pad.
这个，这个，还有这个，就会在同一时间段内被加密
Namely this one and this one. So lets
quickly state the security theorem for a
也就是，这个和这个。现在让我们来简要的陈述一下随机计数器模型的安全定理
randomized counter mode . By now you should
be used to these kind of theorems.
到现在你们应该能熟练运用各种定理了才对
Basically we are given a secure PRF. What
we end up with is an encryption scheme.
基本上，只要我们有一个安全的PRF，那么我们仅需要做的就只有做出一个加密方案
We'll call it E sub CTR, E sub counter
mode, which is semantically secure under a
我们称之为E_CTR，CTR是计数器模式的意思。它在选择明文攻击下是语义安全的
chosen plain text attack. It encrypts
messages that are L blocks long, and
它加密L个分组长的明文信息，
produces cipher text that are L+1 blocks
long because the IV has to be included in
产生L+1个分组的密文，因为IV总是包含在密文当中的
the cipher text. This is for randomized
counter mode. And the error bounds
这是对于随机计数模式的，这是误差范围
are stated over here. It's basically the
same bounds as in the case of CBC
基本上和CBC的误差范围一样
encryption. As usual, we argue that this
term is negligible because the PRF F is
通常情况下，我们会把这个情况忽略不计
secure and we would like to deduce from
that, that this term is negligible so that
因为PRF F是很安全的，我们可以推出这一项是可以忽略的
ECTR is secure. Unfortunately we have this
error term here and so we have to make
因为E_CTR也是很安全的。不幸的是我们有这里的误差项
sure this error term is negligible. And
for that we have to make sure Q squared L
所以我们不得不确保这个误差项是可忽略的。而且我们要确保Q的L次方小于分组大小
is less than the size of a block. And
remember, Q is the number of messages
而且要记得，Q是使用一个秘钥加密的明文数
encrypted under a particular key. And L is
the maximum length of those messages. Now
而L是这些明文里的最大长度
interestingly in the case of CBC we have Q
squared L squared. Has to be less than x.
有趣的是，在CBS下，我们有Q的L的次方，不得不小于x
Which is actually worse than we have for
counter modes. In other words, counter
而我们的计数器模式要好一些
modes can actually be used for more.
Blocks than CBC could. Lets see a quick
换句话说，计数器模式实际上可以比CBC加密更多的分组，让我们来看个简单的例子
example of that. So here is, again, the
error term for counter-node, and remember
这里是计数器模式的误差项
Q is again the number of messages
encrypted with a key, and L is the length
记住Q是用同一秘钥加密的明文数，L是明文数分组
of those messages. And as before, just as
in the case of CBC, suppose we want the
和之前一样，设想我们希望
adversary's advantage to be at most, one
over 2 to the 32. That basically requires
攻击者的优势最多为1除以2的32次方
that this Q-squared, L over X be less than
1 over 2 to the 32. So for AES what
要求Q^2*L除以|X|小于1除以2的32次方
happens is, if you plug in the values X is
2 to 128, 128 bit blocks. So Q times
所以对于AES来说，如果带入|X|=2^128
square root of L should be less than 2
to the 48. This is basically the bound you
所以Q乘以L的平方根应当小于2的48次方
get from plugging in 2 to the 128 into
this bound here. And as a result, you can
这是带入2的128次方后得到的误差上界
see if you're encrypting messages that are
each, 2 to the 32 blocks. Then after 2
结果是，你能看见，如果加密的每条明文都是2的32次方个分组
to the 32 such messages you have to
replace your secret key otherwise
那么之后，你就不得不更改你的的秘钥
randomized counter mode is no longer CPA
secure. So this means we could encrypt a
否则随机计数模式不再是CPA安全的了。也就是说
total of 2 to the 64 AES blocks using a
single secret key. Remember, for CBC the
我们可以使用一个秘钥对所有从2的64次方个AES分组进行加密
corresponding value was 2 to the 48
blocks so in fact because counter mode has
对于CBC来说，这个相关的变量可以是2的48次方个分组的，所以事实上
a better security parameterization in fact
we can use the same key to encrypt more
因为计数器模式有一个更好的安全参数
blocks with counter mode than we could
with CBC. So I wanted to do a quick
所以相比较CBC，我们可以用一个秘钥对计数模型进行更多分组的加密
comparison of counter mode and CBC. And
argue that in every single aspect, counter
所以我想对计数模型和CBC做一个简单的比较。对于每一个方面来说
mode is superior to CBC. And that's
actually why most modern encryption
计数器模式要比CBC高级。这也就是为什么现代的加密方案
schemes actually are starting to migrate
to counter mode, and abandoned CBC. Even
都开始转向计数器模式，而远离了CBC
though CBC is still quite widely used. So
let's look at the comparison. First of
即使CBC依然广为应用。我们来比较一下
all, recall that CBC actually had to use a
block cypher because if you look at the
首先，记得CBC必须使用分组密码。因为
decryption circuit, the decryption circuit
actually ran the block cypher in reverse.
如果你观察译码回路，你会发现它是反向运行分组密码
It was actually using the decryption
capabilities of the block cypher. Whereas
实际上它是使用了分组密码的解密功能
in counter mode, we only use a PRF. We
never ever, ever use the decryption
而在计数器模式中，我们只需要使用一个PRF，我们永远都不会用分组密码的解密功能
capabilities of the block cypher. We only
use it in the forward direction, only
我们只使用正向加密功能
encrypt with it. Because of this, counter
mode is actually more general and you can
因为这，计数器模式用的更为普遍
use primitives like Salsa, for example,
Salsa20, if you remember, as a PRF.
你可以使用Salsa，比如Salsa20，你应该记得这是个PRF
But is not a PRP. So counter mode can
Salsa but CBC cannot. And in essence,
而不是PRP。所以计数模型可以Salsa而CBC不行
counter mode is more general than CBC.
Counter mode, as we said, is actually
本质上，计数模型要比CBC更为一般化，就像我们刚说的
parallel, whereas CBC is a very sequential
process. We said that counter mode is more
他们是可并行的，CBC是一个非常串行化的过程。所以我们说计数器模式更为安全
secure. The security bounds, the error
terms are better for counter mode than
计数器模式的安全上界和误差项比CBC好
they are for CBC. And as a result, you can
use a key to encrypt more blocks in
结果就是，你使用同一个秘钥进行加密的数目要比CBC多
counter mode than you could with CBC. The
other issue is, remember in CBC we talked
还有一件事就是，记得我们讨论过假的补齐分组。
about the dummy padding block. If you had
a message that's a multiple of the block
如果有一个明文信息，它的长度是分组长度的倍数的话
length. In CBC we said that we had to add
a dummy block whereas in counter mode this
在CBC里，我们必须要给它加上一个假的补齐分组，而在计数器模式里则不需要
wasn't necessary. Although, I did want
to mention that there is a variation of
尽管我曾经想提到，有一个CBC变种叫做CBC密文偷窃，可以用来
CBC called CBC with cipher text tiling, that
actually avoids the dummy block issue. So
避免产生假的分组
for standardized CBC, we actually need a
dummy block. But in fact there is a
所以，对于标准的CBC来说，它是需要一个假的分组的
modification to CBC that doesn't need a
dummy block. Just like counter mode.
但实际上确实有这么一种情况导致CBC的修改不需要假的分组，就像计数器模式一样
Finally, suppose you're encrypting just a
stream of one byte messages, and using
最后，我们假设一下，你正在加密一个字节的信息流
nonce encryption with an implicit
nonce. So, the nonce is not
使用隐藏的新鲜值进行新鲜值加密，因此新鲜值不包含在密文里
included in the cipher text. In this case.
Every single one byte message would have
这样说的话，每一个字节的信息都必须都必须被扩展成16字节的分组
to be expanded into a sixteen byte block
and then encrypted, and the result would
然后才能进行加密，结果就会生成一个16字节分组
be a sixteen byte block. So if you have,
like, a stream of 100 one byte messages,
那再假设一下，如果你有100个一字节的信息流组成的流
each one separately would have to become a
sixteen byte block. And you'll end up.
就需要单独将他们扩展为16字节的分组，然后，你就会累成狗了
With a stream of 16 byte cipher texts. So
you get a 16x expansion on the length of
你最终得到的是一连串16字节的密文流，密文长度扩展16倍
the cipher text, compared to the length of
the plain text. In counter mode, of
再与明文的长度比一下，就很清楚了
course, this is not a problem. You would
just encrypt each one byte message by
而在计数器模式中，就不会存在这种问题，你可以加密一字节信息
XORing with the first bytes of the stream
that's generated in the counter mode. So
通过与计数器模式产生的流的第一个字节异或
every cipher text would just be one byte,
just like the corresponding plain text.
这样产生的密文都是1比特的，就像明文一样
And so no expansion at all, using counter
mode. So you see that essentially, every
在计数器模式下，根本不会出现扩展。这也就在本质上说明了
single aspect counter mode dominates CBC.
And that's why it's actually the
计数模型在各个方面都要优于CBC，以及为什么它能这么受欢迎
recommended mode to be using today. Okay,
so this concludes our discussion of chosen
以至于沿用至今。这也就结束了我们对选择明文攻击安全的讨论
plaintext security. I wanted to just
quickly summarize and remind you that
我们来简单的做个概述
we're going to be using these PRP and PRF
abstractions of block ciphers.
还有，我们接下来将会讨论如何运用PRP和PRF来进行实际操作
This is actually the correct way of
thinking of block ciphers and so we'll
这确实是使用分组密码的正确方式
always think of them as either
pseudorandom permutations or pseudorandom
我们通常将他们视为双向伪随机置换或者伪随机置换函数
functions. And then I wanted to remind you
again that, so far, we saw two notions of
我要再提醒一下，迄今为止，有两种安全思维模式
security. Both only provide security
against eavesdropping. They don't provide
这两者都是只针对窃听攻击提供的安全性。
security against tampering with the cipher
text. One was used when the key is only
但是他们不能抵御密文干涉
used to encrypt a single message. The
other one was used when the key was used
一个只用于加密单个密文，另一个只能用于
to encrypt multiple messages. And as we
said, because neither one is designed to
秘钥被用来加密多个明文信息时，如我们所说，因为两个安全都不是
defend against tampering, neither one
provides data integrity. And we're going
为密文篡改而设计的，都不提供数据完整性保护，
to see this as a real problem. And as a
result, in fact, I'm going to say in the
我们知道这确实是个真实且存在的问题，实际上，我想说
next segment that these modes actually
should never, ever be used. You should
在下节你会看到，这些模型其实永远都不会被用到
only be using these modes in addition to
an integrity mechanism, which is our next
而你需要做的就是使这些模型外加上完善机制，这也是我们下节课的话题
topic. Okay, so, so far we've seen
basically for using a, the key once, you
迄今为止，如果你只需要使用一次秘钥
can use stream ciphers or you can use
deterministic counter mode. If you're
那么使用流密码或者确定的计数器模式
gonna use the key many times you could use
randomize CBC or randomize counter mode
而如果你想使用同一秘钥多次的话，就需要使用随机化的CBC或者随机计数器模式
and we're gonna talk about how to provide
integrity and confidentiality. Once we
我们将会讨论如何提供完整性和私密性
cover the topic of integrity, which is our
next module.
而这是我们下章将要学习到的知识